<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jen's Log</title><link href="http://jhamon.github.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://jhamon.github.com/feeds/Learning.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://jhamon.github.com/</id><updated>2012-01-17T00:00:00Z</updated><entry><title>These aren’t your grandma’s flashcards</title><link href="http://jhamon.github.com/Anki.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-01-17T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name>Jennifer Hamon</name></author><id>tag:jhamon.github.com,2012-01-17:Anki.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Richard Feynmann famously bemoaned the way that too many students
memorized instead of thought their way through problems.  But I
disagree: memorizing things is a necessary part of developing a field
of expertise that is too-often neglected.  Sure, it&amp;#8217;s great to be
&lt;em&gt;smart&lt;/em&gt;, but if at the end of the day you don&amp;#8217;t really &lt;em&gt;know things&lt;/em&gt;
then what kind of expert are you,&amp;nbsp;really?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This reality about the need to know things cold is one of the first
hard truths I ran into during graduate school.  I&amp;#8217;m sure anybody who
has worked on a science PhD has been through a conversation like this
(substituting appropriate bits of argot from your own field, of&amp;nbsp;course):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A professor walks up to the blackboard and asks a general knowledge
question.  &amp;#8220;Who remembers the mineral formula for olivine?&amp;#8221;  Or,
maybe, &amp;#8220;Can anyone tell me the difference between a clinopyroxene and
an orthopyroxene?&amp;#8221;  There might be a few mumbles from the class, but
usually there will be silence. I&amp;#8217;m usually on the fence about speaking
up because I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; I know something, but I&amp;#8217;m not 100% sure and am
loath to show ignorance.  Then the professor gives a gruff admonition
that, &amp;#8220;You should really know this for your quals,&amp;#8221; before proceeding
to answer his own question and carry&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mixture of shame, frustration, and anxiety that comes
from not being able to remember those things that are simultaneously
fundamental, familiar, and easy to understand cannot be&amp;nbsp;overstated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I, and I&amp;#8217;m sure others, blame ourselves for these feelings, but the
truth is that nobody in our educational legacy ever gave us the tools
to learn and retain information.  Memorization as a teaching
philosophy has been out of fashion for many years now, so that the
current products of the public education system have never been asked
to &lt;em&gt;memorize&lt;/em&gt; anything.  The sad truth of it is, though, that if you
aren&amp;#8217;t being asked to memorize anything while moving through a
content-based educational curriculum (e.g. history, social studies,
etc), then you aren&amp;#8217;t really being asked to do anything at all of
lasting educational&amp;nbsp;value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Spaced repetition overs some&amp;nbsp;advantages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I know now is that &lt;a href="http://www.wired.com/medtech/health/magazine/16-05/ff_wozniak?currentPage=all"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;spaced
repetition&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
is a huge help in retention and recall of factual information. Memories decay exponentially; without systematic review
eventually of substance just evaporates leaving nothing but the vague
feeling of having seen something&amp;nbsp;before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flashcards are an obvious tool for reviews, but I find them difficult
to make by hand and annoying to carry around.  Fortunately, in the
last decade or so several bits of software have been written to help
people manage large digital collections of electronic flashcards.
These applications, termed &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spaced_repetition"&gt;&amp;#8220;Spaced Repetition
Systems,&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt; help you
schedule reviews to maximize learning over the long&amp;nbsp;term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the most popular&amp;nbsp;are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://ankisrs.net/"&gt;Anki&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (free, cross&amp;nbsp;platform)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.mnemosyne-proj.org/"&gt;Mnemosyne&lt;/a&gt; (free, cross&amp;nbsp;platform)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.supermemo.com/"&gt;SuperMemo&lt;/a&gt; (paid, Windows&amp;nbsp;only)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://orgmode.org/worg/org-contrib/org-drill.html"&gt;Org-Drill&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;part of Org-Mode in Emacs (free, cross&amp;nbsp;platform)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These systems have the user rate themselves on how well they know each
card and then uses an algorithm to figure out when they should study
the card again.  The best time to study a card is right before you
forget it.  Each time the user answers a card correctly the interval
gets a little longer, until pretty soon a card only needs one or two
reps per year to be maintained in memory. Forgetting a card resets the
interval to daily&amp;nbsp;reviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you think you hate flashcards, I&amp;#8217;d recommend giving this
method of study a fresh look.  Really knowing things is such a high, I
think you&amp;#8217;ll quickly come around to liking&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>